<?xml version="1.0" encoding="UTF-8"?>
<!--DOCTYPE metadata SYSTEM "csdgm2.dtd"-->
<metadata>
  <idinfo>
    <citation>
      <citeinfo>
        <origin>U.S. Geological Survey</origin>
        <pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
        <title>USGS High Resolution Orthoimages for State of New Jersey</title>
        <geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
        <pubinfo>
          <pubplace>Sioux Falls, SD</pubplace>
          <publish>U.S. Geological Survey</publish>
        </pubinfo>
      </citeinfo>
    </citation>
    <descript>
      <abstract>
      	Multi-spectral digital orthophotography was produced at a scale of 1:2400 (1 in = 200 ft) with a 12 inch pixel resolution for the New Jersey - State Plane project area.  Digital orthophotography combines the image characteristics of a photograph with the geometric qualities of a map. Orthophoto data is produced through the use of digitized perspective aerial photographs or other remotely sensed image data. This data is processed into a digital product that has been rectified for camera lens distortion, vertical displacement caused by terrain relief, and variations in aircraft altitude and orientation.
      	
      	Acquisition information, processing, accuracies, etc. apply only to the data collected under Task Order G15PD00279. The information reported does not include imagery acquired and produced by the US Army Corps of Engineers (USACE) and AXIS Geospatial. However, tile counts and boundary coordinates include the USACE imagery.
      	
      	This dataset consists of uncompressed, ortho photo tiles formatted as 16-bit, 4-band (RGB and NIR) GeoTIFF images with TIF world files.  A total of 9,201 tiles were produced in NAD83 (2011) State Plane New Jersey, US survey feet; tile size is 5,000 ft x 5,000 ft and uses the NJOIT index.
      	
      	The Microsoft UltraCam Falcon and Eagle large format digital camera was used to capture 4-band (RGB and NIR), 16-bit imagery at a Nominal Acquisition Altitude of 16,480' (AGL) during the Spring of 2015 on the following flight dates:
      	May 29, 2015-A (N344Q; 40312131)
      	May 29, 2015-B (N344Q; 40312131)
      	Apr 1, 2015-A (N344Q; 40312131)
      	Apr 2, 2015-A (N344Q; 40312131)
      	Apr 6, 2015-A (N441MD; 817310)
      	Apr 16, 2015-A (N87WS; 50617043)
      	Apr 18, 2015-A (N441MD; 817310)
      	Apr 19, 2015-A (N170TA; 50811038)
      	Apr 19, 2015-A (N441MD; 817310)
      	Apr 19, 2015-B (N441MD; 817310)
      	Apr 26, 2015-A (N87WS; 60617043)
      	Apr 29, 2015-A (N191TA; 5039383)
      	May 2, 2015-A (N87WS; 50617043)
      	May 3, 2015-A (N87WS; 50617043)
      	      	
      	The Nominal Acquisition Altitude of 16,480' (AGL) was used to capture the imagery.  Supplemental flight lines were also acquired over defined urban areas of Atlantic City, Jersey City, Newark, Camden, and Trenton in order to provide additional imagery to be used in the process of minimizing building lean during orthophotography production.

Maximum and mean differential baseline lengths were not generated for the DVRPC/LVPC/NJ/YCPC orthoimagery project due to the use of Applanix SmartBase software used to process and compute atmospheric errors within a specified GNSS multi-base network.

		SmartBase processing offers a number of significant benefits including:
			The distance to the nearest reference station can be extended well beyond 30 km.
			The time to fix integer ambiguities is significantly reduced.
			The overall reliability of fixing integer ambiguities is increased.
			No special processing is required in the RTK engine, as it is the case for a centralized multi-base approach.

		Due to the complexity of the typical reference station network used in SmartBase processing, determining maximum and mean differential baseline lengths is not feasible for this project.
		
		For the 12 inch GSD Ortho image, horizontal positional accuracy was designed not to exceed 4 feet NSSDA 95% confidence.
      </abstract>
      <purpose>
      	This data depicts geographic features on the surface of the earth.  It was created to provide easily accessible geospatial data which is readily available to enhance the capability of Federal, State, and local emergency responders, as well as plan for homeland security efforts.  This data also supports The National Map.
      </purpose>
    </descript>
    <timeperd>
      <timeinfo>
		<rngdates>
			<begdate>20150329</begdate>
			<enddate>20150503</enddate>
		</rngdates>
      </timeinfo>
      <current>ground condition</current>
    </timeperd>
    <status>
      <progress>Complete</progress>
      <update>irregular</update>
    </status>
    <spdom>
      <bounding>
      	<westbc>-75.5728479790489</westbc>
      	<eastbc>-73.8735217552427</eastbc>
      	<northbc>41.3726259587492</northbc>
      	<southbc>38.9147156201798</southbc>
      </bounding>
    </spdom>
    <keywords>
      <theme>
        <themekt>None</themekt>
        <themekey>12 inch orthoimage</themekey>
        <themekey>rectified photograph</themekey>
        <themekey>rectified image</themekey>
        <themekey>orthophoto</themekey>
        <themekey>natural color orthophoto</themekey>
        <themekey>orthoimage</themekey>
        <themekey>image map</themekey>
      </theme>
      <place>
        <placekt>
        	U.S. Department of Commerce, 1995, Countries, dependencies, areas of special sovereignty, and their principal administrative divisions, Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 10-4): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology.
        </placekt>
        <placekey>US</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>
        	U.S. Department of Commerce, 1987, Codes for the Identification of the States, the District of Columbia and the outlying areas of the United States, and associated areas (Federal Information Processing Standard (FIPS) 5-2): Washington, D.C., National Institute of Standards and Technology.
        </placekt>
        <placekey>NJ</placekey>
      </place>
      <place>
        <placekt>None</placekt>
        <placekey>New Jersey</placekey>
        <placekey>Atlantic County</placekey>
        <placekey>Bergen County</placekey>
        <placekey>Burlington County</placekey>
        <placekey>Camden County</placekey>
        <placekey>Cape May County</placekey>
        <placekey>Cumberland County</placekey>
        <placekey>Essex County</placekey>
        <placekey>Gloucester County</placekey>
        <placekey>Hudson County</placekey>
        <placekey>Hunterdon County</placekey>
        <placekey>Mercer County</placekey>
        <placekey>Middlesex County</placekey>
        <placekey>Monmouth County</placekey>
        <placekey>Morris County</placekey>
        <placekey>Ocean County</placekey>
        <placekey>Passaic County</placekey>
        <placekey>Salem County</placekey>
        <placekey>Somerset County</placekey>
        <placekey>Sussex County</placekey>
        <placekey>Union County</placekey>
        <placekey>Warren County</placekey>
		<placekey>Mid Atlantic</placekey>
		<placekey>East Coast</placekey>
		<placekey>US</placekey>
		<placekey>NJ</placekey>
      </place>
    </keywords>
    <accconst>None</accconst>
    <useconst>
    	None.   However, users should be aware that temporal changes may have occurred since this data set was collected and that some parts of this data may no longer represent actual surface conditions.  Users should not use this data for critical applications without a full awareness of its limitations.
Acknowledgment of the U.S. Geological Survey would be appreciated for products derived from these data.
    </useconst>
    <datacred>Quantum Spatial, Inc.</datacred>
    <native>
    	Windows 7 OS; Microsoft Office products (Word, Excel, Internet Explorer, and Access);  MicroStation version 8;  Intergraph suite of products;  Esri ArcGIS 10;  UltraEdit;  Global Mapper;  GeoExpress 9
    </native>
  </idinfo>
  <dataqual>
    <attracc>
      <attraccr>
      	Radiometry is verified by visual inspection of the digital orthophoto.  Slight systematic radiometric differences may exist between adjacent orthoimage files; these are due primarily to differences in source image capture dates and sun angles along flight lines. These differences can be observed in an image's general lightness or darkness when it is compared to adjacent orthoimage file coverages. Tonal balancing may be performed over a group of images during the mosaicking process which may serve to lighten or darken adjacent images for better color tone matching.
      </attraccr>
    </attracc>
    <logic>
    	All GeoTIFF tagged data and image file sizes are validated using commercial GIS software to ensure proper loading before being archived.   This validation procedure ensures correct physical format and field values for tagged elements.  Seamlines and tile edges are visually inspected.  Seamline mismatches are corrected unless the overall displacement is less than one pixel.
    </logic>
    <complete>
    	Orthoimages are visually inspected for completeness to ensure that no gaps or image misplacements exist within and between adjacent images. These images are derived by mosaicking multiple images to ensure complete coverage. Source imagery is cloud free. Photography was flown during leaf-off in deciduous vegetation regions.
    </complete>
  	<posacc>
  		<horizpa>
  			<horizpar>
  				Please see the Accuracy Analyst report for a detailed report showing the 57 control points measured to produce the NSSDA value of 0.737 meters.
  			</horizpar>
  			<qhorizpa>
  				<horizpav>0.737</horizpav>
  				<horizpae>95% NSSDA confidence interval, meters</horizpae>
  			</qhorizpa>
  		</horizpa>
      <vertacc>
        <vertaccr>There is no vertical component for orthophotos.</vertaccr>
      </vertacc>
    </posacc>
    <lineage>
		<srcinfo>
			<srccite>
				<citeinfo>
					<origin>Quantum Spatial</origin>
					<pubdate>2015</pubdate>
					<title>GPS Photo Control Survey</title>
					<geoform>Model</geoform>
				</citeinfo>
			</srccite>
			<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
			<srctime>
				<timeinfo>
					<sngdate>
						<caldate>2015</caldate>
					</sngdate>
				</timeinfo>
				<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
			</srctime>
			<srccitea>CONTROL</srccitea>
			<srccontr>
				Quantum Spatial performed a geodetic control survey in support of a digital orthophoto production project. The survey was done using the Global Positioning System (GPS). A combination of 68 quality assurance control points that were incorporated in the quality assurance testing of the aerotriangulation. Photo control points have a combined local and network accuracy at 95% confidence of less than or equal to five (5) centimeters horizontally and vertically as determined by the residuals of the network adjustment.  All horizontal and vertical control was prepared under the supervision of a Professional Land Surveyor licensed in the States of New Jersey and Pennsylvania.
			</srccontr>
		</srcinfo>
		<srcinfo>
			<srccite>
				<citeinfo>
					<origin>Quantum Spatial, Inc.</origin>
					<pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
					<title>Georeferenced Single Frames</title>
					<geoform>remote-sensing image</geoform>
				</citeinfo>
			</srccite>
			<typesrc>external hard drive</typesrc>
			<srctime>
				<timeinfo>
					<rngdates>
						<begdate>20150329</begdate>
						<enddate>20150503</enddate>
					</rngdates>
				</timeinfo>
				<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
			</srctime>
			<srccitea>PHOTO</srccitea>
			<srccontr>
				Aerial imagery was acquired using Microsoft UltraCam Falcon and Eagle large format cameras with a flight design that included a total of 4171 exposures in 51 flight lines. Aerial imagery was supplemented with the simultaneous acquisition of airborne GPS/IMU data, which captured the ground coordinate for the nadir point of each photograph. Aerial imagery was exposed at an altitude of 16,480' above mean terrain.
			</srccontr>
		</srcinfo>
		<srcinfo>
			<srccite>
				<citeinfo>
					<origin>Quantum Spatial</origin>
					<pubdate>Unknown</pubdate>
					<title>Aerotriangulation</title>
					<geoform>model</geoform>
				</citeinfo>
			</srccite>
			<typesrc>CD-ROM</typesrc>
			<srctime>
				<timeinfo>
					<rngdates>
						<begdate>20150329</begdate>
						<enddate>20150503</enddate>
					</rngdates>
				</timeinfo>
				<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
			</srctime>
			<srccitea>AT</srccitea>
			<srccontr>
				Softcopy aerotriangulation was performed utilizing the airborne GPS/IMU data, GPS ground control and image coordinate measurements allowing the direct computation of the exterior orientation parameters for each image of the project. Smartbase was used.  Mean differential baseline lengths are as follows:
				
				For March 29, 2015 Mission A (UltraCam Eagle SN: 40312131) the mean baseline length was 30.995 kilometers.
				For March 29, 2015 Mission B (UltraCam Eagle SN: 40312131) the mean baseline length was 53.19 kilometers.
				For April 1, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 40312131) the mean baseline length was 51.445 kilometers.
				For April 2, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 40312131) the mean baseline length was 53.38 kilometers.
				For April 6, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 817310) the mean baseline length was 157.435 kilometers.
				For April 16, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50617043) the mean baseline length was 36.355 kilometers.
				For April 18, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 817310) the mean baseline length was 302.79 kilometers.
				For April 19, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50811038) the mean baseline length was 41.045 kilometers.
				For April 19, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 817310) the mean baseline length was 59.32 kilometers.
				For April 26, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50617043) the mean baseline length was 77.18 kilometers.
				For April 29, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50319383) the mean baseline length was 52.07 kilometers.
				For May 2, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50617043) the mean baseline length was 50.95 kilometers.
				For May 3, 2015 (UltraCam Eagle SN: 50617043) the mean baseline length was 89.64 kilometers.
			</srccontr>
		</srcinfo>
		<srcinfo>
			<srccite>
				<citeinfo>
					<origin>Public Domain Elevation Surfaces</origin>
					<pubdate>unpublished material</pubdate>
					<title>DEM/DTM</title>
					<geoform>model</geoform>
				</citeinfo>
			</srccite>
			<typesrc>DVD</typesrc>
			<srctime>
				<timeinfo>
					<rngdates>
						<begdate>2002</begdate>
						<enddate>2009</enddate>
					</rngdates>
				</timeinfo>
				<srccurr>ground condition</srccurr>
			</srctime>
			<srccitea>DEM</srccitea>
			<srccontr>
				A compilation of topographic land form elevation datasets developed through photogrammetric data capture and/or LiDAR provided from various sources for use in developing digital ortho imagery. Although the pilot was processed with DEMs, the final project will use higher quality surfaces.
			</srccontr>
		</srcinfo>
		<procstep>
			<procdesc>
				Imagery Acquisition:
				Digital aerial imagery was obtained using a large format Microsoft UltraCam Falcon and Eagle equipped with Airborne GPS/IMU covering the entire State of New Jersey.  A total of 51 flight lines with 4171 frames were collected in the spring of 2015 in multi-spectral (RGB and NIR) 16 bits format.  This includes the acquisition of supplemental imagery over the cities of Atlantic City (2 Flight Lines; 18 Frames), Camden (2 Flight Lines; 12 Frames), Jersey City (1 Flight Line; 6 Frames), Newark (2 Flight Lines; 14 Frames), and Trenton (2 Flight Lines; 16 Frames) that was used to minimize building lean in the orthophotography production process.  The imagery was acquired at an altitude above mean terrain of 16,480' to yield a raw pixel resolution of 0.96' suitable for photogrammetric mapping and orthophoto production.  The imagery was collected during leaf off conditions in the spring of 2015 under conditions free from clouds and cloud shadows, smoke, fog, haze, light streaks, snow, ice on water bodies, flooding, and excessive soil moisture. The imagery is also mostly free from foliage, but leaves were beginning to come out towards the end of acquisition in May.  In order to minimize shadow conditions, imagery was obtained during the period of the day when the sun angle was greater than 35 degrees.  For New Jersey, the sun angle was greater than 35 degrees south of US Highway 1 and greater than 40 degrees north of US Highway 1.  The imagery consisted of blue, green, red and near infrared bands.  Imagery for the photogrammetric mapping and digital orthophotos was captured according to the USGS Contract No. G10PC00026; USGS Task Order: G15PD00279; Requisition Reference Number: 0040202231 regarding, snow, haze and cloud cover, and modified as appropriate to accommodate the requirements specific to UltraCam technologies and as specified in this scope of work.
			</procdesc>
			<srcused>RAWs</srcused>
			<procdate>2015</procdate>
			<srcprod>Georefs</srcprod>
		</procstep>
		<procstep>
			<procdesc>
				Control / QC Checkpoint Creation:
				A total of 68 ground based photo control points were established throughout the project area using a combination of conventional and GPS survey methods in order to support softcopy aerotriangulation and photogrammetric mapping meeting the accuracies specified in this Scope of Work.  This control supplemented the exposure station control obtained from the onboard Airborne Global Positioning System (ABGPS) and Inertial Measurement Unit (IMU). Photo control points established for this project have a combined local and network accuracy at 95% confidence of less than or equal to five (5) centimeters horizontally and vertically as determined by the residuals of the network adjustment. Ground control collection followed requirements set forth in USGS Contract No. G10PC00026; USGS Task Order: G15PD00279; Requisition Reference Number: 0040202231, and were modified as appropriate to accommodate the specifications related to ABGPS collection specific to these end photogrammetric mapping requirements. All horizontal and vertical control was prepared under the supervision of Professional Land Surveyors licensed in the states of New Jersey and Pennsylvania.
			</procdesc>
			<srcused>Geodetic control</srcused>
			<procdate>2015</procdate>
			<srcprod>Control</srcprod>
		</procstep>
		<procstep>
			<procdesc>
				Aerotriangulation Process:
				Softcopy aerotriangulation was performed on 2 blocks of imagery. The airborne GPS/IMU data, GPS ground control, and image coordinate measurements were utilized to allow the direct computation of the exterior orientation parameters for each image frame to support the photogrammetric process and orthophoto production.  The adjusted Root Mean Square Error (RMSE) of all horizontal and vertical control points used for any single block adjustment was 1.0 foot or better.  At the same time, residuals on each refined image coordinate remain less than 10 microns and residuals on any horizontal or vertical control point did not exceed plus or minus 0.075 meters.  Within each block, the QA ground survey coordinates were within two times the RMSE (1 meter) of the corresponding AT derived coordinates.
			</procdesc>
			<srcused>ABGPS</srcused>
			<srcused>Control</srcused>
			<srcused>RAWs</srcused>
			<procdate>2015</procdate>
			<srcprod>AT</srcprod>
		</procstep>
		<procstep>
			<procdesc>
				Digital Terrain Model Creation:
				This process involved the development of seamless topographic landform elevation dataset utilizing existing public domain elevation data sets to support the production of digital orthophotography that meet or exceed required orthophoto horizontal accuracy. Existing terrain surfaces utilized for this project included the maximum utilization of government supplied airborne topographic LiDAR bare earth data sets of various vintages, accuracies and post spacing as well as DEM data from the 2015 New Jersey Orthophoto Project as needed to complete a 2015 Statewide orthophoto DEM source. The topographic features included a grid of elevation points and may include break lines that define ridges, valleys, edge of water, transportation features and abrupt changes in elevation.  The final DTM is suitable for orthophoto production only (not suitable for contour generation).  The DTM is used to then generate a Triangulated Irregular Network (TIN) to support orthophoto production.
			</procdesc>
			<srcused>DTM</srcused>
			<srcused>DEM</srcused>
			<srcused>LiDAR</srcused>
			<procdate>2015</procdate>
			<srcprod>DTM/DEM</srcprod>
		</procstep>
		<procstep>
			<procdesc>
				Orthophotography Creation:
				Utilizing all four bands [blue (B), green (G), red(R) and near infrared (IR)] digital orthorectification was performed using bilinear interpolation algorithms resulting in a spatial and radiometric transformation of the digital image from line/sample space into NAD83 (2011) State Plane New Jersey, US Survey Feet. The interior and exterior orientation parameters from the aerotriangulation process were used to project each pixel into the ground coordinate system, while the ortho grade DEM/DTM was used to correct for relief displacement. Radiometric correction software and techniques were used to create orthophoto files that minimize the appearance of image seams and without loss of feature signature. Orthophotos are checked for geometric accuracy, image quality, and are tonally balanced to produce a uniform contrast and tone across the entire project. The individual overlapping orthophoto frames were mosaicked together.  The ortho photos meet a horizontal accuracy of 4 feet or less at 95% confidence level when compared to higher accuracy check points based on NSSDA testing standards.
			</procdesc>
			<srcused>Georefs</srcused>
			<srcused>AT</srcused>
			<srcused>Control</srcused>
			<srcused>DTM/DEM</srcused>
			<procdate>2015</procdate>
			<srcprod>Orthos</srcprod>
		</procstep>
	</lineage>
  </dataqual>
  <spdoinfo>
    <direct>Raster</direct>
    <rastinfo>
		<rasttype>pixel</rasttype>
			<rowcount>5000</rowcount>
			<colcount>5000</colcount>
		</rastinfo>
  </spdoinfo>
	<spref>
		<horizsys>
			<planar>
				<gridsys>
					<gridsysn>State Plane Coordinate System 1983</gridsysn>
					<spcs>
						<spcszone>2900</spcszone>
						<transmer>
							<sfctrmer>0.9999</sfctrmer>
							<longcm>-74.5</longcm>
							<latprjo>38.83333333333334</latprjo>
							<feast>492125.0</feast>
							<fnorth>0.0</fnorth>
						</transmer>
					</spcs>
				</gridsys>
				<planci>
					<plance>row and column</plance>
					<coordrep>
						<absres>1</absres>
						<ordres>1</ordres>
					</coordrep>
					<plandu>survey feet</plandu>
				</planci>
			</planar>
			<geodetic>
				<horizdn>North American Datum of 1983</horizdn>
				<ellips>Geodetic Reference System 80</ellips>
				<semiaxis>6378137</semiaxis>
				<denflat>298.2572221</denflat>
			</geodetic>
		</horizsys>
	</spref>
  <eainfo>
    <overview>
      <eaover>
      	Natural color orthoimagery is organized in three color bands or channels which represent the red, green, and blue (RGB) portions of the spectrum.  Each image pixel is assigned a triplet of numeric values, one for each color band.  Numeric values range from 0 to 255.
      </eaover>
      <eadetcit>U.S. Department of the Interior, U.S. Geological Survey, 1996, Standards for Digital Orthophotos: Reston, VA.</eadetcit>
    </overview>
  </eainfo>
  <metainfo>
    <metd>20151228</metd>
    <metc>
      <cntinfo>
        <cntorgp>
          <cntorg>U.S. Geological Survey</cntorg>
        </cntorgp>
        <cntaddr>
          <addrtype>mailing and physical address</addrtype>
          <address>Customer Services</address>
          <address>U.S. Geological Survey</address>
          <address>EROS Data Center</address>
          <address>47914 252nd Street</address>
          <city>Sioux Falls</city>
          <state>SD</state>
          <postal>57198-0001</postal>
          <country>US</country>
        </cntaddr>
        <cntvoice>1-800-252-4547</cntvoice>
        <cnttdd>1-605-594-6933</cnttdd>
        <cntfax>1-605-594-6589</cntfax>
        <cntemail>custserv@usgs.gov</cntemail>
        <hours>Monday through Friday 8:00 AM to 4:00 PM (Central Time)</hours>
        <cntinst>
        	The above is the contact information for EROS Data Center in Sioux Falls, SD. This is the digital data storage and distribution center for the USGS. Metadata information can also be obtained through online services using The National Map Viewer, at http:/nationalmap.usgs.gov or EarthExplorer, at http://earthexplorer.usgs.gov.
        </cntinst>
      </cntinfo>
    </metc>
    <metstdn>FGDC Content Standard for Digital Geospatial Metadata</metstdn>
    <metstdv>FGDC-STD-001-1998</metstdv>
  </metainfo>
</metadata>